Intentionality is important. How do we
how do we sit down and use this
equipment that has been entrusted to us?
Um
because we can use it to tear down
people. We can use it to tear down
society
or we can use it to build up the body of
Christ.
One of the promises of AI is that we
might arrive at an era of abundance. Um
that's wonderful. And I mean I think
most people would would celebrate that
um more time and more goods. One of the
things though, father, that I that I'm
not entirely convinced with that that
promise that that vision is if we look
at today's society is um that a lot of
people are suffering from loneliness. Um
I think it's something like 50% of young
girls uh under I think it's under 25 are
suffering from from severe uh severe um
anxiety. When you look at technologies
promise it seems obvious that it's that
it can maybe deliver on those goods but
it but it's it is also causing a a wake.
There is a side effect to this stuff.
>> Well first of all Ben thank you for
inviting me. I don't denigrate all at
all technology. I think we can learn all
kinds of things. uh in technology. Uh
but there's something about
everyday
relationships
that we form with people, you know, that
we that we actually look like into
another person's face into their eyes,
you know, and there's something about
like re about being received by another
person about actually talking and having
another person like even like smile or
like actually laugh like there's
something engaging and this is something
that needs to be learned.
First of all, it starts in the family.
It starts out with um you know between
husband and wife and how they treat each
other, how they talk with each other,
how they handle their relationships with
one another. Like um we have
disagreements with people, you know,
with people that we love, with your
wife, with people that I live with in
community. There ruptures happen all the
time. Um, and oftentimes what happens
when we have a rupture with somebody,
uh, we have an old expression that, oh,
it's just water under the under the
bridge. Uh, it'll go down down the
stream and
people just forget about it. And, you
know, but does that really happen? Like,
we remember like we actually remember
how we've been hurt.
Um, and we carry that on all throughout
our life.
So like sometimes there's there's
ruptures in our life that happen that
don't reach a resolution.
They don't have a healing.
If people have bad experiences,
sometimes they'll then want to hide away
from them or avoid those experiences,
which mean that then if you have a phone
that you can then mediate, you know,
mediate those relationships by, you
don't have to do it physically. You
don't have the unpleasant experience,
but maybe there's a moment of growth
that you're avoiding. And one thing that
I've been thinking about, father, um, is
we spend a lot of time alone in front of
screens. And if you have increasing
amount of people um who are opting for
those isolated experiences for for
comfort, for escape, for convenience, as
a spiritual father, as someone who
spends a lot of time um speaking with
people, counseling people, what do you
see?
>> We spend a lot of time on the screen. I
mean, I think
you like if both of us looked at our
screen time right now,
>> just too much just today. Uh and this
week we would both be ashamed of
ourselves like thinking uh you know have
I have I spent uh this much time um you
know engaging with another human being
you know with with real contact uh with
even prayer. I mean, have I spent as
much time every day uh with the living
God in in adoration or or contemplation
or meditation on the scriptures versus
how much time I've spent in in uh
looking at my phone, looking at my uh my
computer. And I think you're right, like
I think what you were getting at um is
that like
with the way they're making technology
nowadays, they
they know how to to to draw you in.
>> They know us better than ourselves in a
weird way. Like those algorithms,
>> even algorithm. Yeah, exactly. That's
the word I was looking for. They they
know what I mean automatically. um they
know what we want, you know, kind of uh
even the patterns, even the the the way
we think even um it it's you can't
replace the way the human mind, you
know, and the way the human mind thinks
and the way the human mind, the way the
heart feels, the way we have emotions.
Uh that can't be replaced. I know what
it's like to have anxiety. Um,
[clears throat] and I I'm not one I'm
not a person who learned about anxiety
through uh a book uh through uh classes,
but I actually feel it. I I know what it
I know what it feels like uh to have uh
uh anxiety disorder. Um and that that
came after um you know, my parents uh
separation and divorce. you know, just,
you know, I just I talk about my
experience because I think it might help
people. Um, like growing up, um, you
know, I was from a loving family. Um,
and, um, after 25 years of marriage, my
my parents, um,
uh, separated and divorced, uh, because
of my dad's alcoholism
and, uh, my mom really tried, you know,
really hard to, you know, make the
marriage work and really sought a lot of
help. She herself was praying a lot and
she was going to to church in adoration
and but you know there there are some
cases where the church does permit you
know separation uh because of you know
trials and and trauma. Um so my mom did
end up leaving um my dad after 25 years
of marriage. Um, and shortly after that,
I had I was just starting my uh journey
into like the sermon on my vocation uh
to the priesthood. And my dad uh called
me on the phone. He he uh threatened
that he was going to take his life and
telling me how he was going to do it. So
that's how anxiety was introduced into
my life, you know, was was through a big
tea trauma, you know, like that, you
know. So, you know, like for 25 years
now, like, you know, I have um you know,
it's a lot better than it was years ago,
but I've I know what it's like to to be
anxious, you know, and to experience the
the effects in the body of a trauma, you
know, like you one of the things I think
uh that we hear often that people hear
often that are anxious,
they're told, "Oh, don't be anxious."
And that that just first of all, it
doesn't validate the person's experience
at all. It's like, okay, yeah, I guess
you're right. I guess I shouldn't be
anxious. So, they they end up pushing
through,
you know, life and the anxiety really
doesn't get better, you know. So I mean
I I've learned to you know just in my
discussions with people and whether it's
in spiritual direction or confession is
like even to validate someone's like
experience
you know like actually enter into it
like gosh like like tell me about that
tell me about you know how you feel tell
me about your anxiety
um and not treat it as something like
like you shouldn't feel this way you So
if somebody is feeling anxious, you
know, somebody's feeling, you know,
anxiety because of, you know, their
experience,
um, you know, that's real. You know,
that that's real. It's, um, you know, I
don't denigrate that at all. You know, I
like to talk with people where they're
at and actually have them explain to me
what does that feel like?
Well, what what are the thoughts uh that
are coming up in your mind when you're
anxious? You know, let's let's talk
about that. Let's get them out. You
know, cuz when you when you actually
talk about that with another human
being, you know, I I don't know about
you, but don't you have a feeling of
like almost like relief?
>> Absolutely. like almost like like and
and I mean we could talk like people
turn to AI in these things into chat
bots and stuff like that but they don't
experience the relief you know they
don't experience the relief in like a a
human contact but actually when you talk
to another human being whether that be a
good friend the priest a counselor you
know somebody who can actually validate
your experience
and like even validate your worth as a
human being, you know, and say, you
know, you're not you're not like
identified by your anxiety.
You have anxiety. You not you're not
you're not anxiety, you know. It's
there's not an equal sign like like you
have a worth like that goes beyond, you
know, your condition, you know. Um I
think that can help a lot. Why do you
think it is that so many people rather
than turning to people who love them or
people who can you know physically be in
the same space with them and help them
get through you know some of these
issues or talk through some of these
problems um why do you think they are
turning to AI and chatbot because
there's there's an interesting graphic
where there's that iceberg and then
there's the um the water at the bottom
and so there's the peak which is these
are things I admit to my wife and then a
little bit below is um is these are
things I admit to my my priest or
counselor, but at the very very bottom
of it uh you know way deep down at the
bottom of the water is these are the
things I told Chhat GPT and I I wonder
what what you think that says about our
society where publicly or openly we we
admit to very few you know suffering of
anxiety or suffering from you know
things that are on our mind and then at
the very bottom are things that we only
tell an AI system and and I wonder if
it's because we're afraid of being
judged if um if there's that kind of
deep dark hole where it's like Okay,
this is an AI, so it's not even real,
but I'm just going to actually simulate
a conversation.
>> I know Mother Teresa would talk about
this. You certainly like like rejection
is a poverty. So, I think a lot of
people are afraid of rejection,
you know, uh just in just even in
forming relationships. So, I think a lot
a lot of guys like they're afraid to be
rejected, you know, they won't ask out,
you know, a girl, you know, on a date
because they're afraid of rejection, you
know, but but they'll talk to
>> a an AI bot because they won't be
rejected, you know, it'll just feed it,
feed it, feed it. So like when we
experience rejection you know in my life
and I have
um so there's like a trail a like like
if I experience rejection now as you
know being 49 all the way back all
throughout my life throughout my
childhood there's like almost like a
like a a trail like breadcrumbs a trail
going back so that it's like a trigger.
M
>> so it's like it's like um
and there's stuff like that I'm sure in
your life in people's lives um and
there's not there's no there's no
resolutions so there's tra there's
traumas there's rejections throughout
our life that that that haven't been
healed
that haven't been affirmed I think even
as adults we can you know speak with
somebody about our the ways that we've
been rejected throughout our life and we
can enter into and that and we do that
relationally you know talking talking
with another human being um I have a a
group that I belong to um it's called
story group and one of my friends
actually started uh something called
Catholic story groups and we actually we
we've done this uh we can do it in
person I've done it in person before
with like five six seven people where we
actually talk about our story
and something in our life that was a
trauma, something that happened in my
life that like in high school or as a
kid that like has deep lasting effects
in our life that we that we feel to this
day.
So there's a healing that there can be
healing that takes place in having like
a affirmation and validation when you're
when you're talking with a group of
people and you're telling your story and
you're telling your experience of what
it actually was like what it felt like
when this teacher
told me in front of the entire class for
instance that I was stupid
that I would never go to college
that I would never do anything with in
my life,
you know. So telling that story what it
was like and how it has lasting
consequences in my life now and actually
be feeling at that moment feeling like
gosh I'm I feel like this abandoned. I
feel like nobody saw me. I feel like
nobody came to my aid. Right?
So there's a moment of healing that
takes place when you're in a group of
people and actually have somebody in the
group
like actually say,
"I feel so mad right now about what that
teacher said to you." Like someone
actually speaks truth. Somebody actually
enters into like your pain. Um and and
and that's that's a moment of healing.
That's a moment of repair that can
happen in one's life and we can't like I
like it's hard to it would hard be hard
to simulate that through like AI through
it's it seems like what we want and what
we need are those real meaningful
confirmations those real meaningful
moments with other people where you can
be vulnerable and trust and I find it
interesting that the AI provides you a
simulation that you know is artificial I
mean the programmers themselves are
saying that it's it's repeating in in
almost mode for mode what it is that you
want to hear from it. And I think that
we know that. But the fact that people
still choose to do that
>> and I'm sure it feels good. It it you
know when when I'm using AI and and I
and I'm typing in something um you know
theologically and I and I'm making a
distinction. and I'm asking a question
based on like the readings of the day
and a saint and applying it to this and
or that and like when the AI says, "Oh,
that's a great distinction." Like that's
a great like like that's a great
thought. You actually feel good.
[laughter]
>> You feel good about yourself.
>> Yeah. But but I think father like you're
you're using it for like a very
practical like like good reason like
it's it's research or it's an an
assistance in the way that it's
constructed for. And I think that that's
that's great. And what I what I'm
worried about is like people putting
their blinders on and really on some
level opting out and and knowing that.
And I and I wonder why that is because,
you know, we spoke a bit about, you
know, anxiety and all that stuff and and
of course, you know, rejection being
being terrifying, but I wonder if it's
the technology that's magnifying the
problem that has always been there, but
it's magnified it to a point where
people really are able to remove
themselves on some level from that
system entirely,
>> remove themselves from actual real
relationship.
>> Yeah. like technologically permitted
abandonment of reality like which is
something that is new but I I feel like
there's that we're approaching a moment
which is maybe maybe at the moment it's
still hypothetical though the fact that
that large percentage of of of young men
are opting out of of dating because you
know you have you know pornographic
substitutes and you have video game
substitutes to the pursuits of real life
you know in that in that heroic sense um
I feel like this is kind of new though
>> opt out of reality What do you mean
living? And that's and that's scary. I
mean, I I I what comes to mind
immediately, you know, um is my dad
telling me, you know, just remember
probably like 5 years ago. I remember
this conversation like uh you I don't
see many kids out. I don't I don't see
uh people playing in the streets um uh
like you guys did when you were kids.
You know, we wanted to go outside. Our
parents had to drag us in. Yeah,
[laughter]
>> I remember playing kick the can and and
and actually going down actually
skateboarding. Um I mean nowadays I have
conversations with people about uh
skateboarding games and them choosing
you know people characters
skateboarders. Um, for instance, uh,
like Bucky Lasic, you know, the Tony
Hawk skateboarder, I think is a a very
popular game. And like they have these
skateboarders who are like professional
skateboarders who are you choose, you
know, as your character, you know, and
and I'm like, well, I actually
skateboarded on the same ramp as Bucky
Lasic. Like, I didn't play the the game,
but I actually I I know who he is. Like,
I saw him. I like I I I have memories
like when I was like 13, 14, 15 years
old him pulling up in his, you know,
pimped out car um and uh stereo blaring
and him getting out and he's a
professional skateboarder and and just
cuz one of my friends knew him growing
up. So
>> that's so cool.
>> It's really cool. I I always like to
show off with that. [laughter]
>> But father, you spent time outside
getting good like like really practicing
hard
>> and it's Yeah. I mean, I spend 3 to four
or 5 hours a day skateboarding uh on
quarter pipes, uh um on rails,
um
>> that's a lot of dedication.
>> Pipes, vert ramps. Yeah. I mean, I you
know, bloodied my hands, bloodied my
knees, um you know, broke bones. Um it
takes hard work. It takes dedication. Um
you know, to do that. Uh but yeah.
Father, what do you say to the kid who's
like, "Yeah, Father, that's great that
you did that, but I can do, you know, a
version of that on the video game." I
think I mean, at least I would say it's
not the same It's not the same thing.
>> That's hard to hear. That's hard because
I know I think I have experience of
doing actually going out and and doing
it. Um uh and and and having the sense
of accomplishment of of trying to
master, you know, what a trick is uh how
a trick is done. Uh and falling over and
over and over again. Uh and then getting
up and then actually, you know, doing
the after how many times? Hundreds of
times of failures,
you know, to to reach a point where, you
know, after a couple weeks, um maybe a
couple months, you actually know how to
do this trick and you have the muscle
memory of doing that trick. But you're
not going to get to that point of
mastery of doing the trick unless you
fall.
>> Which means also like a metaphor for
like the rejection. Like you're not
going to
>> fall.
>> Yeah.
>> We need sometimes like we're going to
have failures. We're going to have times
in our life where we fall, where we mess
up.
>> Um where we say the wrong thing. Um
I I think you know e even in giving
speeches I mean how how much have we
done public speaking you know even
something like this I mean I get kind of
anxious when I talk you know sometimes I
don't know what I'm going to say or if
I'm going to say something the right way
if I'm going to stutter on my words
but I I learned that you know when
especially when I entered religious life
one of the biggest things for me when I
entered religious life was like a fear
of speaking
that I'm not going to be able to talk in
front of people because and this goes
all the way back to like that rejection
of in woodshop that experience of being
told I was stupid, right? So like I I
had to get over that. Like I had to like
in a sense reach through that and keep
persevering through that. And so through
the years of um being in seminary and
then being a frier, being on EWTN, I
mean, I never thought in a million years
that I'd have a a microphone in front of
me and that I'd be talking, you know,
with with people, be talking, you know,
you know, I I like to think that I mean
like when we preach when we preach and
teach the gospel, when we're giving a
homaly,
I know what I know what I like when I
when I listen to a a homaly, I don't
like to be talked at. I don't like to be
preached at like to be like I actually I
think it's more effective when you're
like like a homaly is supposed to be
like a dialogue. Like the way like
Fulton Sheen the preach I think he's a
great example. I tried to learn from him
and the way that he preached and and
taught is the way that he would pause
and the way that he would speak. He
would give people time to like think
like to pause and not just be like I I
there's some people that just like
preach and they preach a million miles
an hour at you and after 10 minutes I I
don't know what the they said. I don't I
have no idea what they said and I don't
care, [laughter] you know, and like like
I want to be like I want to be in
relationship with people you and I think
that like I think the most effective
communicators are people that like bring
you into relationship. Yeah. I think I'm
thinking of people like you know one of
my friends Chris.
Chrisonic is a is a great communicator.
the way that he he gets across to people
through the media, through podcasts,
like he draws people in through like
relationship, you know, he looks into
the camera, you know. I think, you know,
Mother Angelica had had [clears throat]
that um that gift that when she looked
into the camera, uh she said, "Family,
we're going to talk about Jesus
tonight."
And she would talk about real things.
She'd talk about suffering. mother
talked about her own, you know,
sufferings in life, her own failures
even. And why do you think people
actually liked her and identified with
her because like they saw themselves?
They're like, "This lady's real. Like
she's not putting on a fake show. Like
she's real and like like if she can be a
Christian then then I think I can like I
think I can overcome my failures if this
lady has." And father, what what do you
think Mother Angelica would think of of
kind of this day and age, this kind of
AI powered age also where, you know,
people are talking about AI film
studios, they're talking about AI books,
they're talking about AI, you know,
pastors and and priests and and sermons.
>> Um, I think she'd be very worried
actually. Um, I I don't think Mother
Angelica is afraid of technology. Uh, I
think we know that. I mean, there's all
kinds of technology that we use at EWTN
through the years. Um, uh, innovative
stuff that, you know, Mother Angelica
was like a pioneer of, right?
U, but I think that she would always go
back to silence,
spending time in silence before the
blessed sacrament. Why? Um, I think that
she had so much to say
in front of things like this, in front
of a a microphone, in front of the TV.
Uh, I think she had so much to say
because she because she spent so much
time in recollection.
Um, it wasn't just because that she was,
you know, educated and went to a
pontipical university and, you know, she
didn't do any of those things.
I think that she really
like knew what to say and and knew how
to talk to people based on her
relationship with Jesus
bar like first and foremost bar none.
like her relationship with Christ, her
experience of being loved by God,
I think when it comes back to it,
everything in her life that she spoke
about on television that she
communicated all came back to her
relationship,
her relationship with Jesus. Um and I
think that's that's what we can teach
people uh as priests as as lay people um
you doing communication um we can teach
people to pause uh to take time in their
life to pray
to be silent uh I think Pope Leo
actually talked about that um recently
in in uh when you talk a lot about
education the importance of
contemplation the importance of silence
Um, and these things are are crucial uh
in the Christian life uh not to be
completely immersed with noise. Uh
because I know what that's like and you
do too, Ben. And we've talked about this
a lot. It's like we at the end of the
day, we are tired. We are we are dead.
Uh we don't even want to pray at the end
of the day because we've been bombarded
by noise and and screens and technology
all day long.
I think when we maybe start the day in
recollection, start the day in silence,
um have periods throughout the day in
silence.
I I often as as chaplain of uh EWTN, I'm
I'm the employee chaplain for ETN. So
uh I try and encourage employees uh to
pray throughout the day to take time to
pray uh because I see what a difference
it makes in our productivity in the way
we write articles in the way we handle
ourselves with people. Um,
I I I think there's a lot to be said
with just taking time to pray, um, to
spend time in in silence and eucharistic
adoration. Not just going to mass, but I
think prolonged periods of eucharistic
adoration. And just start with five
minutes a day,
even five minutes a week, 10 minutes a
week before the Eucharist. just sit
there, just be silent and talk to him,
tell him what's going on. He already
knows. Um, but I I think we need to to
recover that.
>> And father, um, you know, on a on a
practical level, where do you see AI
potentially being a real tool, a real
helper?
>> Well, um, for me, um, I'm a auditory
learner, so I I use it all the time, uh,
in reading documents. uh a document that
would take me like literally days or
weeks to get through because of
comprehension. Uh I think when I read
something from uh beginning to end like
going from paragraph to paragraph I have
a hard time focusing. Um so when I have
something um
when I read and hear it uh through an
app called speechify I use all the time
um and I even today I was using it you
know to kind of go through a document I
see the text being um highlighted you
know so I'm I'm actually engaging my
senses I'm I'm looking at the text I'm
reading and at the same time I'm hearing
So I can get through a whole document
within, you know, less than a couple
hours that would normally take me
probably a week to go through. And I
feel like I actually learn it better by
doing it that way by by engaging the
senses. And that's all that's used
through that's AI technology. Mhm.
>> Um also um you know sometimes we're busy
in in homaly preparation and if we're
preaching every day uh if we have like
talks to do um you know sometimes I
think it's helpful to get like um a
start
uh in homaly preparation maybe for the
weekend or a couple days out you know I
might put in um just something something
like um I'm preaching a homaly
uh in a couple days or tomorrow on these
particular readings and I'll put in the
readings. Um then I'll also put uh just
some questions like uh or I'll put it's
a it's a saint day. It's St. Maria
Grey's feast day. It's St. Pope St. John
Paul II's feast day. Did John Paul II
say anything about this gospel in his
homalies uh during when he was pope? Did
Pope Benedict say anything about this
particular gospel of the good Samaritan?
Did St. Augustine say anything about
this in relation to Catholic education?
Enter.
Bam.
And you have like this whole corpus of
stuff to work with. And so I can read
through it and be like, "Oh, that's a
great start. I mean, this is it's
getting my mind ready in preparation for
preaching." Um, and it just it gives me
crumbs to deal with. It gives me stuff
to pull from that I can use this this uh
um you know kind of information that AI
gives you uh for for good purposes to
preach the gospel to communicate with
people. Um and you can always ask more
questions too as the time goes along. Um
you can kind of build on that. So
>> I think we can use we can use it
responsibly. I think we can it's all in
it's all in our intention and how we use
uh technology. We can use technology to
be, you know, to to take uh to take take
take, you know, for ourselves and to be
like greedy, right? But I I think I
think we like we need to be open-handed,
you know, like um what's the psalm?
Open-handed he gives to the poor. His
justice, his prosperity endures forever.
So if we live as like open-handed
and like not wanting to clutch things,
not wanting to even clutch or possess
technology is like mine mind, but like
use as a good steward using technology
and in a healthy way and wanting to, you
know, first of all be a better steward
of creation better and to hand on the
faith to hand on the faith that I've
received. I think that's a healthy way
of looking at using technology properly
is not wanting to have it possess you
because we can let technology possess us
but I think in a healthy way uh is how
how are we using technology and not
allowing it to possess us but do we
possess it you know rather than have it
possess us
>> one thing that I've I've seen and this
has been on kind of Catholic media Um
there's been, you know, public
intellectuals who are who are Christian
who who've talked about this is kind of,
you know, the fear of the demonic inside
of AI. There's people, you know, kind of
going through those gradients who who
very much feel that we're we're
summoning the devil when we're talking
about AI, that these that these are that
these are um dark forces um that are
also, you know, creating a system that
that is very scary. Well, we want to be
connected to again going back to the
primary relationships, you know, that
you know uh that we are in the state of
grace uh that we are [clears throat]
participation in the sacraments that
we're receiving uh holy communion uh
often in the state of grace and that uh
we go to confession often of receiving
the sacrament of of Christ's mercy and
and just
living in God. that that's going to help
the way that we navigate technology,
too, cuz we're not going to be seeking
out false reality. We're not going to be
seeking out um uh sinful behaviors.
And basically, I mean, you know, quite
frankly, I think we're not going to be
opening up doors.
CS Lewis says that hell is everybody's
back turned away from one another. And I
think all of us can say, "Yeah, I've
experienced that." Like I've experienced
like some hell in my life, some being
turned away from people like like like
cut off from people, desolation from
people, like separation from people,
even separation from God, you know. Um
but heaven is actually relationship
communion
actually speaking like loving
fully loving fully engaged in another
person's life. That's what heaven's
going to be like. So we can we can live
heaven now
or we can leave hell now. You know I
think that's that's our choice. Um now
can technology help us to be better
communicators?
Um, sure. You can follow in the
footsteps of Carlo who was recently
absolutely it can help us to do to do
great things like he wanted to bring
people to the Eucharist
like so so he developed he put he put
Eucharistic miracles online and how many
people have benefited from his putting
together on the computer
a database of all the eukar eucharistic
miracles in the world. How many people
have come to know Jesus in the real
presence and come to full communion with
the church because of this 15year-old
boy who died you know of leukemia who's
now canonized a lot you know so we can
use technology for incredible things and
I'm sure people
will come up with with even more
creative ways to you know to use um you
know technology and and to use it in a
in a in a Christian way in in a moral
way. Intentionality is important. How do
we how do we sit down and use this
equipment that has been entrusted to us?
Um
because we can use it to tear down
people. We can use it to tear down
society
or we can use it to build up the body of
Christ
and to help contribute to the healing of
the world, the salvation of the world.
>> I love that. Father, maybe one last
question while I have you here. I feel
that you know this these years these
times there's a lot of there's a lot of
tension a lot of fear a lot of um kind
of negativity around the future and um
you know as as a as a as a man of God as
a as as a father can I ask um as we end
like what gives you hope what keeps you
optimistic the best thing I do is to
hear confessions
the holiness of the church is manifested
in the confessional that's where you see
how good people really are um It's it's
it's not the the sins that people
confess um the weaknesses, the failures
that people confess um uh that it
doesn't get me down. It doesn't, you
know, somehow crush me and think, "Oh
gosh, you know, uh again, you know, I'm
hearing this again and again and again."
Uh no actually the confessional is a
place where
uh we as sinners as penitants come into
contact with the mercy of God.
And it is a miracle
for anybody to humble themsself
to get down on their knees and to
confess into another person's ear
the most shameful things that they've
done in their life. You know, people
that have been away from the faith for
uh decades. Um, you I always tell people
all the time, think about um
if you've only had 5 hours left on this
earth before you meet God [snorts] um
and that's that you're going to meet God
face to face. Like what is it in your
life that you are holding on to? If
there's anything in your life that you
haven't confessed or as forgiveness for,
what is it in your life that um that you
need to ask God forgiveness for for
healing for you and let it go? Say it
out loud. Christ wants to you to let it
go and to to seek forgiveness, to seek
reconciliation, to seek healing. Um and
that happens in the sacrament of
penance. You know, I think people um
probably do that on through chat bots.
You know, they probably talk about their
failures and they probably receive
advice from from AI from chat bots and
stuff and they receive, you know, things
back. But in confession, you know,
you're coming before the throne and of
grace.
Um and there's something there's a
wisdom. I mean, Christ is the one who
instituted the sacrament of penance. I
always like to say say to say that um
Jesus Christ is the best psychologist
that ever existed. [laughter] He's God.
He's a God man. But he knows human
psychology. He knows that we need to
hear in our ear. We need to hear that
we've been forgiven, that we've been
absolved, you know. And those those
words that I say, you know, when I was
able to give uh my dad um uh absolution,
you know, the moment he died, you know,
um I I looked down and put my stole on.
I had my oils, you know, and I said, you
know, God the Father of mercies through
the death and resurrection of his son
has reconciled the world to himself and
poured out the Holy Spirit for the
forgiveness of sins. through the
ministry of the church. May God grant
you pardon and peace. And I absolve you
from your sins in the name of the Father
and of the Son and of the Holy Spirit.
Amen. And I dip my finger in the holy
oil, anointed his forehead through this
holy anointing. May the Lord in his love
and mercy help you with the grace of the
Holy Spirit, anointed his hands. May the
Lord freeze you from sin save you and
raise you up. and I went straight into
the apostolic pardon. By the authority
granted to me by the apostolic sea, I
grant you a full pardon and remission of
all your sins. In the name of the father
and the son and the holy spirit. Amen.
And my dad died
at that moment like he died as I was
giving him last right as the apostolic
pardon so that that he he would close
his eyes to this world and that he would
open his eyes to see the he would see
the face of Jesus. You know only God can
arrange something like that. You know,
so like like the brokenness like like
even in my own relationship with my
father having some brokenness in that in
that relationship uh because of my
parents' divorce and separation, you
know, having my dad going back to my my
dad saying to me about, you know, that
he was going to take his life and how he
was going to do it. That's where anxiety
enters into my life was through my my
dad doing that, right?
But God allowing me at that moment to
give my dad absolution.
That's God healing. That's God healing
through relationship. So I am incredibly
grateful.
>> That's beautiful. And on that note, I
think um this is a wonderful uh spot to
end. Um Father John Paul, thank you so
much uh for your time today.
>> You're welcome.
>> Um and this is a reminder to all of you
to go to confession, to speak to real
people,
>> to live in the real world. Um, thank you
so much, Father.
>> You're welcome. It's good to be here,
Ben.